Guide to the Missionary Ephemera Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Photographs, Series XII
  - Africa
    - Collection of 7 press photos of the visit of King Baudouin to the Belgian Congo in 1955. (Box 18, Folder 14)
      This collection focuses on missionary activities in the region. Shown are Monseigneur Bigirumwami, Vicaire Apostolique de Nyunde; Monseigneur Van Waeyenbergh, rector of the University of Louvain in the Congo, sisters working at the hospital for the Mining Union of Haut-Katanga, St. Boniface students, the opening of a new church, and senior Orthodox and Jewish leaders.
    - Three photographs of the Barotse people in the area of Rhodesia. Accompanying the photographs is a brief history of the people and King Lewanika., no date (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - Collection of 16 photographs of a Mass in Rwanda, with military members and local clergy., 1951 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - Collection of 6 photographs from the Mission in Malemba, Congo. Each photograph is labeled on the reverse side., 1930 (Box 18, Folder 17)
    - YWCA Lagos Nigeria photograph collection. Contains 13 photographs, all of which are described on the reverse side with the people identified., 1947 (Box 18, Folder 18)
    - A collection of 28 photographs of African people and scenes., no date (Box 18, Folder 19)
    - Photo album belonging to a husband and wife bound for the CMS Mission in Kaloleni, Kenya., 1934 (Box 18, Folder 21)
      The missionaries were teachers at St. John's secondary school at the Mission. The album begins with their voyage aboard the famous ship Dunbar Castle (in 3rd class). A number of people are referenced by name. They visit St. Helena, and there are a number of photos of the locals. They also visit Durban and Capetown in South Africa, photographing churches along the way. They then make their way to British East Africa by ship, reaching Kaloleni in August. There are photos of Dr. Allen and Sister Clarke at the CMS Mission Hospial, and a panorama 3-photo collage of the Mission. There are numerous photographs of local Christianized natives, student group photo (with the two teachers), gruesome site of a dead local at the Mission hospital, and local embroidery class. There is a photo of a Mrs. Patterson aboard a train leaving Beira, found for Salisbury. The Kaloleni Mission is located in Giryama in Kilifi District in Kenya. Some of the photos contain descriptions. 117 photographs in all.
    - Photograph album of missionaries in Africa. 97 photographs without captions. Slightly more than half of the photos show natives and native scenes., Early 1930s (Box 18, Folder 20)
    - Commerical missionary photograph album tracing the steps from the ocean voyage on the Liberty Ship Rochefort, bound for French Equatorial Africa., no date (Box 18, Folder 22)
      Visits include Mauretania, Senegal, and Gabon (St. Marie de Liberville Mission). There are also photographs of the staff of Dr. Schweitzer (Dr. Guy de Lange), the tuberculosis clinic, lepers at the mission, Dr. Emeric Percy, and construction of a building enterprise from the proceeds of the Nobel Peace Prize award in 1953. 32 photographs and a June, 1954 newspaper article on Schweitzer.
    - Photograph album of a Girls' Mission School in Uganda. All of the photographs are labeled with names of people and places., 1949 (Box 21, Folder 1)
    - Photograph album of Algerian photos taken by someone interested in missionary work. Contains 78 photographs. Most of the photographs have captions., no date (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - Photograph album full of mission photos from South Africa. The photographs are all labeled and the album has the title, "Scenes in South Africa Illustrating Native Life.", no date (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - Photo album belonging to a Belgian couple that visited Father Antwerpen at the Mission at Roechoebi (also known possibly as Buhonga) in Rwanda., 1948-1950 (Box 21, Folder 4)
      Photo album belonging to a Belgian couple that visited Father Antwerpen at the Mission at Roechoebi (also known possibly as Buhonga) in Rwanda, 1949-1950. Also covered are the trip from Antwerp in September, 1948, Elizabethville, Honzi, Rwagonika, Indebergen, Karuzi, Costermansville, Idjenda, N'Gozi, and Karoezi. Mostly on the life of a colonial couple. Includes 62 photographs, most of which are described on their reverse sides.
    - Photo album of Swedish missionaries in Ethiopia. Most of the photographs are labeled., no date (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - Photograph album full of photographs of scenes of the daily life of natives and a foreign missionary in Malawi. The photographs are all labeled., no date (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - 3 photograph albums from a missionary in Lombolombo and Wafanya in the Belgian Congo., 1940-1964 (Box OV10, Folder 1)
      This collection with labeled photographs covers all aspects of life on a Mission station. Many missionaries and Belgian workers are shown by name. A more detailed description is included in the folder.
    - Photograph album of missionary in Uganda and Kenya, 1927-1932 (Box 31, Folder 7)
  - Asia
    - Set of 50 large format photos of Catholic missionary activity in India and Pakistan., no date (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - 11 photos from a mission in India (Fr. B). Each photo contains lengthy descriptions on the back., 1953-1971 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - Collection of 65 photographs of missionaries and mission work in Japan, no date (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - Collection of 25 photos from pre-communist China taken by a Catholic priest doing missionary work, including working with lepers., no date (Box 19, Folder 4)
      Some of the pictures have descriptions on the backs, such as of lepers who live outside the city walls, "kiddo" and female lepers, and groups of children described as "still pagans". There are also photos of Chinese altar boys, Chinese First Communion, men on horses, and a group of nuns in a boat. There is a mention of Father McCormack's mission. Several of the pictures mention Kongmoon South China. The priests in those pictures are Joe Sweeney and John Coulehan, as well as Bishop James E. Walsh. The picture on the ship mentions they are headed for Culivan. The group of children in front of the Temple is in Pang Yang. The group of priests was taken in Saiko. There is also mention of Tai Shan. Father Tom Malone is pictured with the lepers. There are a couple of other cities named, but the handwriting is very difficult to interpret.
    - 8 photographs in this Anglican photograph collection from Singapore., December 19, 1958 (Box 19, Folder 5)
      Shown are Henry Wolfe Baines (1905-1972), Bishop of Singapore, Sister Ede, and Lady Goode (wife of the Governor) visiting the Anglican hospital. Also shown are Dr. Crow and Health Minister Bzaba. In other photographs, the children are performing a nativity play.
    - 12 Asian photographs. Some of them are labeled with people's names including: Father Duncan, Mr. Shorock, Mrs. Jessie C. Duncan, and British Baptist missionaries., no date (Box 19, Folder 16)
      One photograph is dated 1909, but others are clearly much later. One is labeled as being taken in North-West China. Most of the photographs have no labels on them.
    - Press photo collection of 20 photos from the French evacuation of Vietnam., March 13, 1955 (Box 19, Folder 7)
      This collection focuses on the Catholic Mission at Go Cong on the Mekong River. According to the photo descriptions the city of Dijon adopted the refugees of Go Cong. Images of the French Chaplain General for the region is trying to understand the needs of the refugees, refugees inundating the Mission, church services, etc.
    - Photograph album of the Protestant Mission in Amoy, China., 1906 (Box 19, Folder 8)
      The photographs are all labeled, including references to Hakka School, Amoy School, Chang-pu, and Kio-than Church. This album is from the Manchu period and includes 18 photos.
    - Photo album from a missionary in New Guinea with thirteen photographs. It does not include dates or descriptions., no date (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Photo album relating to missionary work in China by the Sisters of Charity of Vincent de Paul., Early 20th century (Box 22, Folder 1)
      This album includes photos about their work in Chusan/Zhoushan, Zhejiang, and Shanghai, and appears to refer to one nun who died in Shanghai in 1942. A word document included with the album describes the Sisters and the photo album in detail.
    - Album of 215 photographs, all missionary content, during the warlord period in China., 1930s (Box 22, Folder 2)
      Images include those of Chinese pastors, Christian weddings, Sunday school, prayer meetings, war damage to churches, military hospitals, and casualties of war. Several missionaries are mentioned by name in the album.
    - A well-documented photo album (122 photos) of the Jesuit Missionaries of Lyon., 1930s (Box 22, Folder 3)
      Many of the photos seem to be professional photos for the press and part of an archive. Most of the photos are dated and labeled with their location.
    - Photograph album of Asian missions photographs. Some photos are labeled, but most are not labeled. The album is green and was originally made for post cards., no date (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - Photograph album documenting the activities and personnel of various Protestant Missionary groups, principally in Japan., 1901-1938 (Box 22, Folder 5)
      Most of the many pictures contained in the album are labeled. An article describing the album is included with it.
    - Album of photos from China and Japan, 1930 (Box 32)
    - Albums of photos from India, 1930s (Box 32)
  - Europe
    - Press photo of the Albert Schweitzer memorial in Oppenheim Germany, 1958 (Box 20, Folder 1)
    - Photo of a group of missionaries from all over the world gathered for "Missieweek" in Belgium., 1928 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Other
    - Group of 5 photos of a Catholic Mission in Gonzalez, Texas. Mentioned by name are Sisters Bridget, Bernadine, and Vialo. Also a number of students mentioned., 1929 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - Printed Missionary Album of missionaries from the Foreign Mission Board in Richmond, VA., no date (Box 20, Folder 4)
      Some pages are missing from the album. The missionaries are grouped alphabetically under countries in the following order: China, Africa, Italy, Brazil, Argentina, Mexico, and Japan.
    - Photo of 11 missionaries, giving their names and destinations., 1905 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - Photograph of a Roman Catholic Mission School. The rest of the caption is hard to read., no date (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - Folder 1 of 2 of a Collection of 221 photographs from the archive of the Mission Society Oblats de Marie Immaculee, active in the North America polar region., 1914-early 1940s (Box 20, Folder 7)
      Most of the photos contain descriptions on reverse and the collection dates from 1914 to the eve of World War II. Many missionaries are identified by name, some rare photos of air, rail and river transport used by missionaries, Eskimo life, different chapel interiors, grottos, martyrs, many different missions shown by name, etc. Some of the photos contain people who were subsequently used in postcards.
    - Folder 2 of 2 of a Collection of 221 photographs from the archive of the Mission Society Oblats de Marie Immaculee, active in the North America polar region., 1914-early 1940s (Box 20, Folder 8)
    - Photo album of the Madras Conference of Missionaries., December, 1938 (Box 20, Folder 9)
      Most of the photographs have labels. The Missionaries in the album work in many different countries including India, China, Egypt, Philippines, Japan, Sri Lanka, Holland, Argentina, Mexico, Liberia, Burma, South Africa, and Java.
    - Photographs taken by Leon V. Kofod - Africa, Asia, Iran, ca. 1940s (Box 32)
    - Photo booklet: "Reunie van de Gerepatrieerde Broeders uit Oost en West", no date (Box 32)
    - Seven framed photos of David Livingstone Memorial, Blantyre, Lanarkshire, Scotland (Box OV6)
  - Tilburg Mission
    The photo archive of the Holy Family Mission, Tilburg, Netherlands. Some photos identified in Dutch. Includes work in Indonesia, Borneo.
    - Individuals, scenes, worship spaces (Box 23, Folder 1-13)
    - Buildings, funeral ceremony, boats, scenes (Box 24, Folder 1-11)
    - Mission stations, schools, individuals (Box 25, Folder 1-12)
    - Missionaries (Box 26, Folder 1-4)
    - Individuals, ceremonies, scenes (Box 27, Folder 1-9)
    - Indonesia, Timor (Box 28, Folder 1-7)
    - Java, Borneo, Chili (Box 29, Folder 1-9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 30, Folder 1-9)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 31, Folder 1-6)
- Lantern Slides and Glass Negatives, Series XIII
  - Africa
    See detailed listing in box.
    - Negative glass plates 1-16 - South Africa: Amanzimtoti, Boers (Box 33)
      Including: Historic Tree, Dr. Adams' Grave, Adams House, Old Shop and Cart, Palm and Cypress, Jubilee Boys, Kitchen, Dormitory, Dining Room, Natal Boer War - Majuba, Colenso, Ladysmith, Machine Gun, Boers, Boer Wagon, Farm School Illovo
    - Plates 17-32 - Portraits of Africans (Box 33)
      Including: Woman and Child, Topknot, standing, Mboshi, Topknot long, Girl with Gourd, Women with Treakle, Girl Dancing Costume, Wedding Dance, Man and Wife, Three boys greeting, Two men, Two Old Sinners, Coolie Women, Market Durban, Snake Umvoti. Amamba
    - Plates 33-53 - Natal Christians (Box 33)
      Including: Wedding, Ladumas Wife and Child, Daniel Zama, 2 Nozincwaki, Evely, Senaye, Daisy, Girl, Beira Train, Station, Jetty, Kraal, School boys, Woman and Child, Swiss Mission Church
    - Plates 54-67 - South Africa, Inanda (Box 33)
      Including: Groups of Men of Mission, Meeting at Inanda, McCords and Talors first arrival, Lawrences first arrival, Bates Girls, Cowles Children, Inanda Umvoti House
    - Plates 68-82 - Mt. Silinda, East Coast Trip (Box 33)
      Including: Mill at Work, Fumbanda, Chikore School, Dr. Thompson's clinic, Thompsons girls, Kilindini, Ruwenzori, Port Said, Man and Woman of Azores
    - Plates 83-104 - Mozambique Lowlands (Box 33)
      Including: Trip with Taylor, Crossing Buzi do, Chilinda's Kraal, Three Natives, Portuguese family, Mhlanganios development, Policemen
    - Unidentified lantern slide (Box 33)
  - China: Lin Collection
    - Slides from Bureau of Visual Instruction, Chicago (Box 42)
    - Slides from Northern Baptist Convention - Changning (Box 42)
    - Slides from Hui Wen Academy (Box 42)
    - Slides from Canadian Presbyterian Mission Board (Box 43)
    - Slides from Red Star Series (Box 44)
    - Slides from Presbyterian USA Series (Box 44)
    - Slides from T.H. McAllister, N.Y. (Box 44)
    - Slides from China and the Chinese Illustrated Series (T. H. McAllister) (Box 44)
    - Slides from Methodist Episcopal Series (Box 45)
    - Slides from Interchurch Series (Box 45)
    - Slides from The World Service Commission (Box 45)
    - Slides from Christian Lecture Bureau (Box 45)
    - Slides from Charles Killie, 1900-1916 (Box 46)
    - Slides from Edward Van Altena Series (Box 47)
    - Slides from Keystone View Company (Box 47)
    - Slides from Taylors Winnipeg Set (Box 47)
    - Slides from Underwood & Underwood, NYC (Box 47)
    - Slides from China Manufacturing Set, Greater NY Slide Co. (Box 48)
    - Slides from Boxer Rebellion Set (Box 48)
    - Slides from Peking Series (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous slides (Box 48)
    - Miscellaneous slides (Box 49)
    - Slides of river town (Box 49)
    - Slides from the Studio of Annette Karge, Schools Series (Box 49)
    - Slides from China Culture Series (Box 49)
    - Miscellaneous sets of slides (Box 50–52)
  - China: miscellaneous
    Additional China-related lantern slides are available in Record Group 271, The Lin Collection of Lantern Slides and Photographs
    - Miscellaneous lantern slides 1-30 (Box 39)
      See detailed listing in box. Includes Christian schools, scenes and people.
    - Edward H. Smith collection lantern slides 1-50 (Box 40)
      See box for detailed listing. These slides came to the Library via Edward H. Smith. They include slides from various sources, such as the Interchurch World Movement of North America, Annette Karge studio, and others. Include schools, people, scenes, buildings.
    - Edward H. Smith collection lantern slides 51-84 (Box 41)
      Includes images of famine relief work, baby tower, people, schools, scenes.
  - India
    - Lantern slides 1-24 (Box 38)
      See box for detailed list. Includes: scenes and people
  - Japan
    - Lantern slides 1-55 (Box 34)
      See in box for detailed listing. Includes: Yokohama Kaigan Church, Street Preaching by Rev. Hubert Kuyper (RCA), YWCA, Salvation Army, American Bible Society, Ferris Seminary, Settlement Work, Christian schools
    - Lantern slides 56-112 (Box 35)
      See detailed listing in box. Includes: Christian schools and colleges, Toyohika Kagawa, St. Luke's Mission for Lepers, Yoshida University, Buddhist temple, Michi Kawai, YMCA in Tokyo - John R. Mott
    - Lantern slides 113-168 (Box 36)
      See detailed listing in box. Includes: Tokyo YWCA, scenes, buildings, people
    - Lantern slides 169-174 (Box 37)
      Scenes, with people
  - Middle East
    - Lantern slides 1-58 (Box 37)
      Scenes of the Holy Land
    - Lantern slides 59-68 (Box 38)
      See box for detailed listing. Includes: Scenes from the Holy Land